<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Sameer Manek</title>
 <link href="http://sameermanek.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://sameermanek.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2015-09-05T12:18:41-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://sameermanek.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Sameer Manek</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Dr. Uber or How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Employees</title>
   <link href="http://sameermanek.github.io//2015/09/06/uber-employees/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sameermanek.github.io/2015/09/06/uber-employees</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past few months, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/07/06/gigs-with-benefits&quot;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt; has been &lt;strike&gt;focused&lt;/strike&gt; fixated on whether Uber will be forced to reclassify drivers from contractors to employees, it has ignored a bigger question: what would be the effect of Uber employing millions of drivers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://recode.net/2015/07/14/uber-could-have-to-pay-an-additional-209-million-to-reclassify-its-drivers-in-california/&quot;&gt;re/code&lt;/a&gt; analyzed Uber’s drivers in California and estimated that employment would cost them an incremental $200 million compared to Uber’s current California revenue of $250M (Uber takes 20% of all UberX transactions and gives the other 80% to the drivers). This could be disastrous to Uber’s current business model and would probably force them to increase prices to users and reduce hourly pay to drivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, this might be the best possible outcome for Uber. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;network-effects&quot;&gt;Network Effects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber’s current business model is heavily reliant on network effects (commonly called a virtuous cycle), David Sacks tweeted quite eloquently. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidsacks/status/475073311383105536&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/david sacks twitter.png&quot; alt=&quot;David Sacks&#39; virtuous cycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://abovethecrowd.com/2014/07/11/how-to-miss-by-a-mile-an-alternative-look-at-ubers-potential-market-size/&quot;&gt;Bill Gurley&lt;/a&gt;, an early investor in Uber, described in more detail why these network effects justify Uber’s valuation and dominance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, &lt;a href=&quot;http://therideshareguy.com/how-to-drive-for-uber-and-lyft-at-the-same-time/&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/Ride-Sharing-Company-Comparisons/Can-you-be-a-Lyft-UberX-and-Sidecar-driver-at-the-same-time&quot;&gt;drivers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/2014/08/04/technology/uber-lyft/&quot;&gt;switch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pando.com/2014/12/03/uber-vs-lyft-a-former-driver-compares-the-two-services/&quot;&gt;between&lt;/a&gt; Uber and Lyft or use both simultaneously. The reason is fairly well understood by economists: low costs of multi-homing on both sides of the marketplace. Because it is almost trivially easy to have accounts and apps for both Uber and Lyft (as a driver or as a rider), ridesharing is not currently a winner-take-all market. In fact, Uber and Lyft could coexist the same way as different credit card networks, ad-supported streaming video services, and instant messenger apps continue to exist. This concept is known as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/26118/1/555836088.PDF&quot;&gt;multi-homing&lt;/a&gt; and is fairly well documented in literature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Uber and Lyft are forced to employ their drivers, it would be impossible for drivers to work for both simultaneously and very difficult to switch from day to day. Therefore, multi-homing would be essentially impossible for drivers – this would strengthen the already-extant network effects and change ridesharing into a winner-take-all market, which would help the incumbent, Uber.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, if the gig-economy shifts from a contractor- to employee- based model, the largest players – Uber, Postmates, Instacart, et al – would be protected from smaller potential competitors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be the best possible thing that could happen to Uber.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>To log or not to log Part 1</title>
   <link href="http://sameermanek.github.io//2015/03/28/log-scales-1/"/>
   <updated>2015-03-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://sameermanek.github.io/2015/03/28/log-scales-1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed a frustrating phenomenon: the use of linear scales where a log scale would be much more appropriate. While people are more conscientious of deceptive charts now more than ever, misleading scales continue to be an issue. This is my brief rant against them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have no idea whether this choice of scales is intentional or oversight, increasing awareness of users and makers seems like a suitable first step regardless. The purpose of this post and the following (short/occasional) series of posts is to give good reasons and cases in which log scales should be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exponential-growth&quot;&gt;Exponential Growth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most obvious case for using a log scale rather than a linear scale. It seems like a forgone conclusion that when plotting a timeseries of values which naturally grow exponentially, one should use a log scale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;singapore&quot;&gt;Singapore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, in the past week alone I’ve seen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hbs.edu/faculty/units/bgie/Pages/default.aspx&quot; title=&quot;BGIE Department, where the flaw was found&quot;&gt;Harvard Business School&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/&quot;&gt;The Economist&lt;/a&gt; inappropriately use linear scales. Both extremely well-respected and generally unbiased, they nonetheless presented quite misleading views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2015/03/lee-kuan-yews-singapore&quot; title=&quot;Lee Kuan Yew&#39;s Singapore&quot;&gt;Economist presented a graph&lt;/a&gt; quite like the one below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gdp_linear.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of GDP per Capita&quot; /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They concluded that this graph clearly showed how dramatic Singapore’s rise has been. While I agree with the conclusion, their visualization made it nearly impossible to tell that China’s rise has been similarly outstanding (even more so in the past 2 decades), or that post-war Japan was similarly meteoric. A better graph would have been the one below, with a log scale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gdp_log.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of GDP per Capita with a Log Scale&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nigeria&quot;&gt;Nigeria&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nearly identical situation, a professor of mine presented a graph like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gdp_nigeria_linear.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of GDP per Capita of Nigeria&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She claimed that this showed how Nigeria was struggling against the other BRINCS countries (Brazil, Russia, India, Nigeria, China, South Africa). To potentially oversimplify a long and complex history, Nigeria has been seen as a future economic powerhouse for the past 50 years, but various political, regional, and social issues have interfered. However, there has been substantial growth over the past decade and a half under the most recent series of leaders. The graph presented barely showed an uptick in GDP per capita, when in reality, GDP growth in the 2000s has been over 3%, in line with some other resource-dependent BRINCS countries (Brazil and South Africa). I think this point would have been clear had a log scale been used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gdp_nigeria_log.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of GDP per Capita of Nigeria&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exponential growth is the most straightforward case. While both the examples above were related to money, it truly applies to any case of exponential growth: money, population, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code used to generate the graphs above is available &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/log_scales_1.R&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The data for this post came from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ggdc.net/maddison/maddison-project/home.htm&quot;&gt;The Maddison Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Data-Based Analysis of Hacker News</title>
   <link href="http://sameermanek.github.io//2015/02/09/hn-analysis/"/>
   <updated>2015-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://sameermanek.github.io/2015/02/09/hn-analysis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Or: 2048 Con, asking Edward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending a little too much time reading Hacker News, I decided to take a more systematic look at what ends up on HN and what does well. This analysis inspired the alternate title – read on to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a quick reminder, &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; is a website about a wide-range of subjects – everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9015092&quot;&gt;philosophy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8940723&quot;&gt;design&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8980047&quot;&gt;job postings&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9018247&quot;&gt;programming languages&lt;/a&gt;. Hacker News, or as my classmates called it “that hacker website”, is frequently compared to &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddit.com&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;. A similar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.randalolson.com/2013/03/15/a-data-driven-guide-to-creating-successful-reddit-posts/&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; of reddit was pretty interesting, so I wanted to explore how Hacker News would compare (albeit with a more exploratory approach).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of note: I did this entirely for fun; don’t take it too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-are-posts-written&quot;&gt;When are posts written?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More items are posted on weekdays, generally around midday (EST). This is consistent with my expectations – that most people who post on Hacker News are doing so from the US and Europe. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of posts by day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, if we overlay each day on the same scale, we can see that posts occur later on weekends and continue into the night. I.e., I’m not the only one who’s wasted a Saturday night on Hacker News!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts_hour.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of posts by time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of popularity of posts, there’s little relationship between time of day and popularity.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/points.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of average points vs time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that there is a relationship between day of week and popularity of the posts. This relationship is statistically signifiant (using a non-parametric &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mann%E2%80%93Whitney_U_test&quot;&gt;Mann-Whitney U Test&lt;/a&gt;) and I think more clear using boxplots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/points_day.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of points by day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-posted&quot;&gt;What is posted?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most interesting things to me about Hacker News is the diversity of posts. Below is a plot that shows how frequently a post comes from any site in each month. A couple slight caveats though: I only included sites that accounted for ≥2% of the posts in a month (everything else is in the ‘Other’ category), and I foolishly included ‘co.uk’ as it’s own site. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diversity.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of sources&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is pretty clear that while there is a tech focus (techcrunch, ycombinator, wired, etc), no single site accounts for more than a tiny portion of the posts. I repeated this analysis for high scoring posts (&amp;gt; 100 points) and found essentially the same result. For comparison, roughly 60% of posts on reddit link to imgur. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a similar analysis of the users who submitted posts and high-scoring posts and again found very limited concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, on to topics. To begin, I wanted to see whether it was possible to categorize topics based only on their title. Of course, I first made a wordcloud of the titles (very important step in the scientific process).
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/wordcloud_all.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wordcloud of titles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that, using a k-means clustering algorithm (an unsupervised learning technique) on the overlapping words, I was able to create categories that seemed pretty meaningful. However, I found that these categories were not robust; i.e., when I reran the clustering algorithm I’d get new categories. The few that were fairly consistent were: Show/Ask HN, Google, and Windows/Microsoft. A few of the categories shown below are pretty interesting: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘attack’ category includes both ‘nuclear’ and ‘ddos’. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘color’ category includes both ‘blind’ and ‘palette’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘day’ category includes ‘zero’ and ‘demo’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s an entire category for ‘love tablet’. It is best not to examine this too much.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/wordcloud_25.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wordcloud of categories&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shouldn’t be too surprising. Working with very short ‘documents’ means that coincident single words will define entire categories. This technique works better when you can compare longer documents. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More seriously, in the future I’d like to see whether I can find a better way to categorize the posts, likely using the content on page they link to (difficult) or comments on HN (more doable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wanted to see whether any words were strong predictors of high/low scores. To do so, I ran linear regressions on the number of points for each post, and the presence of each word in that post. For example, I would look for a correlation between the number of uses of the word ‘google’ in a title and the points that post scored. Because the number of uses in the word is generally binary (either 0 or 1), this is roughly the same as asking “is the average score higher for titles using this word than for titles not using this word?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/word_scatterplot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scatterplot of words vs score&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then filtered these out to exclude uncommon words and words with an insignificant impact on the total point scored and found the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/significant_words.png&quot; alt=&quot;Expected increase in score by word&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So using words like ‘iphone’ and ‘hn’ are correlated to lower scores, but words like ‘2048’ and ‘broke’ correspond to higher point totals. Apparently using ‘hn’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7988216&quot;&gt;three times&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8561849&quot;&gt;one title&lt;/a&gt; didn’t help improve scores (or maybe these posts were just a little too meta).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concluding-thoughts&quot;&gt;Concluding thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While none of the findings here are all that important, I think they are rather interesting. Especially the last few items: the (in)ability to classify only using the title and the relative importance of some titles over others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, lots of these same tactics can be useful for more serious work, and it’s nice to have a data set on which to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
